<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div key="C6_1925">
    <head>THE SIXTH CANTO</head>
    <lg>
        <l><rest>“</rest>THE tale of thy deeds, Odysseus!” and Tolosan</l>
        <l>Ground rents, sold by Guillaume, <lb/>ninth duke of Aquitaine;</l>
        <l><note>Eleanor</note>Till Louis is wed with Eleanor; the wheel. . .</l>
        <l>(“Conrad, the wheel turns <lb/>and in the end turns ill”)</l>
        <l>And Acre and boy’s love . . . for her uncle was</l>
        <l>Commandant at Acre, she was pleased with him;</l>
        <l><note>Louis VII</note>And Louis, French King, was jealous <lb/>of days unshared</l>
        <l>This pair had had together in years gone;</l>
        <l>And he drives on for Zion, as “God wills”</l>
        <l>To find, in six weeks time, the Queen’s scarf is</l>
        <l>Twisted atop the casque of Saladin.</l>
        <l>“For Sandbrueil’s ransom.”</l>
        <l>But the pouch-mouths add,</l>
        <l>“She went out hunting there, the tuft-top palms</l>
        <l>“Give spot of shade, she rode back rather late,</l>
        <l>“Late, lateish, yet perhaps it was not too late.”</l>
        <l>Then France again, and to be rid of her</l>
        <l>And brush his antlers: Aquitaine, Poictiers!</l>
        <l>Buckle off the lot! And Adelaide Castilla wears the crown.</l>
        <l>Eleanor down water-butt, dethroned, debased, unqueen’d,</l>
        <l>For five rare months.</l>
        <l>Frazzle-top, the sand-red face, the pitching gait,</l>
        <l><note>Henry II</note>Harry Plantagenet, the sputter in place of speech,</l>
        <l>But King about to be, King Louis, takes a queen.</l>
        <l>“E quand li reis Louis lo entendit mout er fasché.”</l>
        <l>And yet Gisors, in six years thence, was Marguerite’s. And Harry <i>joven</i></l>
        <l>In pledge for all his life and life of all his heirs</l>
        <l>Shall have Gisors and Vexis and Neauphal, Neufchastel;</l>
        <l>But if no issue, Gisors shall revert</l>
        <l>And Vexis and Neufchastel and Neauphal to the French crown.</l>
        <l>A song: <i>Si tuit li dol el plor el marrimen</i></l>
        <l><i>Del mon</i> were set together they would seem but light</l>
        <l>Against the death of the young English King,</l>
        <l>Harry the Young is dead and all men mourn,</l>
        <l>Mourn all good courtiers, fighters, cantadors.</l>
        <l>And still Old Harry keeps grip on Gisors</l>
        <l>And Neufchastel and Neauphal and Vexis;</l>
        <l>And two years war, and never two years go by <lb/>
            but come new forays, and “The wheel</l>
        <l>“Turns, Conrad, turns, and in the end toward ill.”</l>
        <l>And Richard and Alix span the gap, Gisors, <note> Alix, sister of<lb/>Philippe-<lb/>Auguste </note></l>
        <l>And Eleanor and Richard face the King,</l>
        <l>For the fourth family time Plantagenet</l>
        <l>Faces his dam and whelps, . . . and holds Gisors,</l>
        <l>Now Alix’ dowry, against Philippe-Auguste</l>
        <l>(Louis’ by Adelaide, wood-lost, then crowned at Etampe)</l>
        <l>And never two years sans war.</l>
        <l>And Zion still</l>
        <l>Bleating away to Eastward, the lost lamb,</l>
        <l>Damned city (was only Frederic knew</l>
        <l>The true worth, and patched with Malek Kamel</l>
        <l>The sane and sensible peace to bait the world<note> Frederic II <lb/>and Malek <lb/>Kamel </note></l>
        <l>And set all camps disgruntled with all leaders.</l>
        <l>“Damn’d atheists!” alike Mahomet growls,</l>
        <l>And Christ grutches more sullen for Sicilian sense</l>
        <l>Than does Mahound on Malek.)</l>
        <l>The bright coat</l>
        <l>Is more to the era, and in Messina’s beach-way</l>
        <l>Des Barres and Richard split the reed-lances</l>
        <l>And the coat is torn.</l>
        <l>(Moving in heavy air: Henry and Saladin.</l>
        <l>The serpent coils in the crowd.)</l>
        <l>The letters run: Tancred to Richard:</l>
        <l>That the French King is</l>
        <l>More against thee, than is his will to me</l>
        <l>Good and in faith; and moves against your safety.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg>
        <l>Richard to Tancred:</l>
        <l>	That our pact stands firm,</l>
        <l>	And, for these slanders, that I think you lie.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg>
        <l>Proofs, and in writing:</l>
        <l>	And if Bourgogne say they were not</l>
        <l>	Deliver’d by hand and his,</l>
        <l>	Let him move sword against me and my word.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg>
        <l>Richard to Philip: silence, with a tone.</l>
        <l>Richard to Flanders: the subjoined and precedent.</l>
        <l>Philip a silence; and then, “Lies and turned lies</l>
        <l>“For that he will fail Alix</l>
        <l>“Affianced, and Sister to Ourself.”</l>
    </lg>
    <lg>
        <l>Richard: “My father’s bed-piece! A Plantagenet</l>
        <l>“ Mewls on the covers, with a nose like his already.<note> Convention <lb/>of Messina </note></l>
        <l>Then:</l>
    </lg>
    <lg>
        <l>In the Name</l>
        <l>Of Father and of Son Triune and Indivisible</l>
        <l>Philip of France by Goddes Grace</l>
    </lg>
    <lg>
        <l>TO all men presents that our noble brother</l>
        <l>Richard of England engaged by our mutual oath</l>
        <l>	(a sacred covenant applicable to both)</l>
        <l>Need not wed Alix but whomso he choose</l>
        <l>We cede him Gisors, Neauphal and Vexis</l>
        <l>And to the heirs male of his house</l>
        <l>Cahors and Querci Richard’s The abbeys ours</l>
        <l>Of Figeac and Souillac And St Gilles left still in peace</l>
        <l>Alix returns to France.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg>
        <l>Made in Messina in</l>
        <l>The year 1190 of the Incarnation of the Word.</l>
    </lg>
    <lg>
        <l>Reed lances broken, a cloak torn by Des Barres</l>
        <l>Do turn King Richard from the holy wars.</l>
        <l>And “God aid Conrad</l>
        <l>“ For man’s aid comes slow,” Aye tarries upon the road,</l>
        <l>En Bertrans cantat.</l>
        <l><note>Bernart of <lb/>Ventadour</note>
            And before all this</l>
        <l>By Correze, Malemort</l>
        <l>A young man walks, at church with galleried porch</l>
        <l>By river-marsh, a sad man, pacing</l>
        <l>Come from Ventadorn; and Eleanor turning on thirty years,</l>
        <l>Domna jauzionda, and then Bernart saying:</l>
        <l>“My Lady of Ventadorn</l>
        <l>“ Is shut by Eblis in, and will not hawk nor hunt</l>
        <l>“ Nor get her free in the air,</l>
        <l>nor watch fish rise to bait</l>
        <l>“ Nor the glare-wing’d flies alight in the creek’s edge</l>
        <l>“ Save in my absence, Madame.</l>
        <l>“	<i>‘Que la lauzeta mover,’</i></l>
        <l>“ Send word, I ask you, to Eblis, you have seen that maker</l>
        <l>“ And finder of songs, so far afield as this</l>
        <l>“ That he may free her, who sheds such light in the air.”</l>
    </lg>
    
</div>
